<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<lothistory xmlns:bibtex="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:wtm="http://wtm.cornell.edu"
    xmlns="http://wtm.cornell.edu" menu="Lot History" xml:id="lothistory">

    <metadata class="main">
        <mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" version="3.3">
            <titleInfo xml:id="cottagelotstitle" class="maintitle">
                <title>History of the Cottage Lots at Ely Lake</title>
            </titleInfo>
            <abstract displayLabel="Content description">
                <wtm:p> This text outlines the history of land and cottage ownership among members
                    of the Ely and related families, specifically around Ely Lake in Montrose, PA. </wtm:p>
                <wtm:itemize>
                    <wtm:item> Early Ownership \&amp; Construction: In 1911, the Ely brothers
                        (Everett F., Luther S. Sr., and Edgar C.) built a family cottage on Edgar C.
                        Ely's lot, which was shared for vacations. Chester Watrous, a
                        brother-in-law, built the fireplace and chimney. </wtm:item>
                    <wtm:item> Land Transfers \&amp; Divisions: Over the years, various lots
                        (including Lot \#4, Lot \#2, Lot \#23, Lot \#5, and Lot \#1) were transferred and
                        divided among family members like Frank T. Ely, Luther S. Ely Jr., Edna Ely
                        Otto, Herman H. Otto, Charles T. Otto, Maurice Otto, Emily A. Adams, and
                        Walter C. Adams. </wtm:item>
                    <wtm:item> Cottage Relocation \&amp; Repairs: The original family cottage, in
                        need of repairs, was given to Edna Ely Otto and her husband Herman H. Otto,
                        who moved it in sections and rebuilt it on a new foundation on their lot. </wtm:item>
                    <wtm:item> Later Sales \&amp; Inheritance: In later years, properties were sold
                        and inherited, such as Frank T. Ely's property being inherited by Jerald Ely
                        and then sold to Kenneth Ely, and Luther S. Ely Jr. and his wife selling
                        their lot and cottage to Jerald Ely. </wtm:item>
                </wtm:itemize>
            </abstract>
        </mods>
    </metadata>

    <page n="1">
        <p>April 1986 </p>
        <p><span class="emph">History of the Cottage Lots at Ely Lake Belonging to the Ely Families
            </span> as remembered by Luther S. Ely, Jr. Families </p>
        <p>(Some dates are taken from the deeds of some of these lots.) </p>
        <p>About 1911, Grandfather Ammi Ely<metadata>
                <mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" version="3.3">
                    <note> Ammi Ely (9 Dec 1824 - 14 Mar 1914) was born in Brooklyn, Pennsylvania.
                        Ammi's grandfather, Ammi Ely (1789 - 1842) was the first settler at Ely
                        Lake. In early 1800 -- and after Revolutionary War -- his father Gurdon Ely
                        (1796–1873) settled in Brooklyn, PA. Ammi had the farm on side of camp where
                        Greenwood, Hultz and Grimly are. Original house is gone. Tom and Drine
                        Makosky own that property. Ammi had a carding mill at ELy Lake outlet -
                        further down. He also had a feed and sawmill on the Meshoppen Creek
                        (41.62338, -75.96681). Power to operate carding mill came from lake. Ammi
                        had a dam there that raised the lake about 10 feet. Ammi is short for
                        Ammiruhama. Ammiruhama was also the name of Ammi's grandfather. </note>
                </mods>
            </metadata> had five lake lots surveyed and marked off. He gave one lot to each of his
            four children then living in Pennsylvania, namely, Everett F. Ely<metadata>
                <mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" version="3.3">
                    <note>Everett Franklin Ely (Sep 1866 - 1946)</note>
                </mods>
            </metadata>, Luther S. Ely, Sr.<metadata>
                <mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" version="3.3">
                    <note>Luther Samuel Ely (27 Dec 1863 - 15 Dec 1942)</note>
                </mods>
            </metadata>, Edgar C. Ely<metadata>
                <mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" version="3.3"><note>Edgar Charles Ely (14
                        Jun 1870 - 24 May 1956)</note>
                </mods>
            </metadata> and Edith<metadata>
                <mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" version="3.3">
                    <note>Edith Alice Watrous (22 Feb 1859 - 18 Jan 1908)</note>
                </mods>
            </metadata>, was Ammi's daughter). The first lot (\#1), on the west boundary of the Ammi
            Ely farm, was retained by Ammi Ely as part of his farm. Each of these five lots was
            measured from the center of the township road to the low water line of Ely Lake, and was
            fifty (50) feet in width at right angles (see <ref class="sketch" refid="sketch1">Sketch
               \#1</ref>). </p>
        <image id="sketch1" src="sketch1" class="sketch">
            <caption>Sketch 1</caption>
        </image>
        <image id="sketch2" src="sketch2" class="sketch">
            <caption>Sketch 2</caption>

        </image>
        <image id="sketch3" src="sketch3" class="sketch">
            <caption>Sketch 3</caption>

        </image>
        <image id="sketch4" src="sketch4" class="sketch">
            <caption>Sketch 4</caption>

        </image>
        <image id="sketch5" src="sketch5" class="sketch">
            <caption>Sketch 5</caption>
        </image>

        <p>In the summer of 1911 the three brothers, Everett F. Ely, Luther S. Ely, Sr. and Edgar C.
            Ely, built the family cottage on the Edgar C. Ely lot. This cottage was shared by the
            four families for vacations for many years. Brother-in-law, Chester Watrous, built the
            fireplace and chimney. </p>
        <p>Sometime in the 1920's, Luther S. Ely, Sr. gave his lot (Lot \#4) to his sons, Frank T.
            Ely and Luther S. Ely, Jr.. Frank T. Ely then built his cottage on the East side of this
            lot in 1926. On January 25, 1923, Edgar C. Ely bought the former Reynolds' farm on the
            West side of Ely Lake. This property included a farm house and about ninety (90) acres. </p>
        <p>Later, Edgar C. Ely, nor his children had any desire to own Lot \#3 at the Lake, so he
            gave it to his brother, Luther S. Ely, Sr. (see <ref class="sketch" refid="sketch2"
                >Sketch \#2</ref>). Soon thereafter Chester F. Watrous died and Luther S. Ely, Sr.
            bought his lot (Lot \#2) from his widow, Louise Watrous (June 5, 1924). Louise Watrous
            was Chester's second wife. Luther S. Ely, Sr. then gave this Lot \#2 to his son, Luther
            S. Ely, Jr. The deed is dated February 4, 1933, although he was given the lot much
            earlier than that date. </p>
        <p>Luther S. Ely, Jr. began building his cottage January 15, 1933 after his father had given
            him the lot. The cottage was ready for use, although not completely finished, by the
            fall of 1934. </p>
        <p>Sometime following the death of Luther S. Ely, Sr. in December 1942, no other family
            member wanting the family cottage and lot, Luther S. Ely, Jr. divided the lot with his
            brother, Frank T. Ely. Frank took the East half of Lot \#23 and Luther the West half (see
                <ref class="sketch" refid="sketch4">Sketch \#4</ref>) The family cottage was in need
            of repairs. None of the other sisters wanted it except Edna Ely Otto and it was
            therefore given to Edna Ely Otto and her husband, Herman H. Otto, who had purchased a
            lot from Herman's brother, Charles and his son, Maurice Otto. This lots joins the east
            side of the Everett F. Ely Lot \#5. The family cottage was moved, in sections, and
            rebuilt on a foundation on their lot. </p>
    </page>
    <page n="2">
        <p> Everett F. Ely's children were not interested in his Lake lot \#5, so he gave it to Frank
            T. Ely. As a result of this, Frank's lot is one hundred twenty-five (125) feet wide.
            (See <ref class="sketch" refid="sketch5">Sketch \#5</ref>). </p>
        <p>On June 21, 1937, Charles T. Otto sold his Lot \#1 to Luther S. Ely, Jr. This is the lot
            which was originally retained as a part of the Ammi Ely farm and had later been
            inherited with the farm by Charles Otto and his son, Maurice Otto. Luther S. Ely, Jr.
            sold the west half of this lot to his sister, Emily A. Adams and her husband, Walter C.
            Adams. He retained the east half and the addition of this half lot made the Luther S.
            Ely, Jr. lot one hundred (100) feet wide. (See <ref class="sketch" refid="sketch5"
                >Sketch \#5</ref>). </p>
        <p> The division of these lots remains the same as of January 1, 1986 although the ownership
            of them has changed. </p>
        <p> Frank T. Ely died on November 8, 1980. Jerald Ely inherited his property and has since
            sold it to his son, Kenneth Ely and wife, Yasuko in the Spring of 1981. </p>
        <p> Luther S. Ely, Jr. and his wife, Jeanne, sold their lot and cottage to Jerald Ely and
            wife, LeJune in May of 1986. </p>
        <p> Dates recorded in this history were obtained from deeds, the diary of Luther S. Ely,
            Sr., from the memory of Luther S. Ely, Jr. and from other family members. </p>
    </page>
</lothistory>
