<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<settlers xmlns:bibtex="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:wtm="http://wtm.cornell.edu"
    xmlns="http://wtm.cornell.edu">
    <metadata class="main">
        <mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" version="3.3">
            <titleInfo xml:id="settlerstitle" class="maintitle">
                <title>Early Ely Lake Settlers</title>
            </titleInfo>
            <abstract displayLabel="Content description">
                <wtm:p> This text describes early settlers of the area around ELy Lake.  
                    It appears contain notes and outlines that may have been intended to form a formal chapter.</wtm:p>
            </abstract>
        </mods>
    </metadata>
    
    <page>
        <p>First settler at Ely Lake was Anni Ely - In early 1800-and after Revolutionary War - his
            father Guden Ely settled in Brooklyn Pa. Anni had the farm on side of camp where
            Greenwood, Hults <esc>&amp;</esc> Grinly Original house is gone - Tom <esc>&amp;</esc> Divine Makusty own that
            property. </p>
        <p>Anni had a carding mill at outlet -further down - he also had a grist mill on the
            Meshopper Creek. </p>
        <p>Power to operate carding mill from lake -- he had a dam there that raised the lake about
            10 ft. </p>
        <p>The scout comp land was owned by L. S. Ely Sr. and his brother E.C. Ely. </p>
        <p>Prior owners of the two farms consisting the scout land were the Rogus farm and the Kent
            farm. </p>
        <p>These two farms were purchased by two brothers Shirley and Hamen Stevens. Stevens went
            into the cattle raising business, having one of the Holstein herds in the area.</p>
        <p> Tragedy struck in form of a heavy spring snow that collapsed the building killing most
            of the herd. </p>
    </page>
    <page n="2">
        <p> As a result of the loss there was a sheriff sale and my grandfather <esc>&amp;</esc> Uncle Ed 
            bought the two farms at the sheriff sale. </p>
        <p> The Stevens brothers were honorable men and even after the sheriff sale, they poid the
            balance to their debtors. </p>
        <p> In about 1920 a Mame? Rittenhoase  from Scanton asked permission to bring a group of girls to camp in an area in vicinity of
            Salorore Hall. </p>
        <p> The next year or so - 1921-22 - the first 12 1/2 acres were bought by the scounts from my grandfather.</p>
        <p> --- This was mostly all farm land --- practically all fields.</p>
        <p> Dpud and <esc>&amp;</esc> Canale Luther mowed around lake to the water edge with horses <esc>&amp;</esc> mowing machine.
             </p>
        <p> At turn of century was the end of era where all the forest was cut down. </p>
        
        <p> In 1927 scouts purchased remainder of the two farms from Grandfather <esc>&amp;</esc> Uncle Ed.</p>
        <p>
            About the same time, LSE planted 10,000 evergreen trees on N. shore area of </p>


    </page>
    <page n="3">
        <p> </p>
        <p> houseboats. Charles Kent and Bill Cameron assisted by my uncle Luther Ely Jr. </p>
        <p> In the area was the huge Oak Tree </p>
        <p> Just above the ash tree was a barn that my Dad took down in about 1925 and used the
            lumer and timbers to build a cottage in 1926 -- floated across the lake. </p>
        <p> In the nineteen fifties the last purchase of scout land was amde from Uncle Ed Ely's heir -- From Apple Book -- around and past the outlet.  In 1948 (c) the last purchase of scout land swas made from cexcle El Ely's keirs. - From
            </p>
        <p> Uncle Ed and Aunt Harriet Ely had beautiful summer near the outlet. </p>
        <p> A show place of beautiful flower gardens, gold fish pond with lady fountain. </p>
        <p> E.C. Ely was director in Pioneer Drive Bank Colale Pa. </p>
        <p> Garden clubs met here - along with mary guests, including frequent visits by girl
            scout campers and staff. Uncle Ed had great appreciation for girl scouting. </p>
    </page>
    <page n="4">
        <p> Other properties </p>
        <p> Ssaac Babeuch - now Jeralyn <esc>&amp;</esc> Lanny Adems. This house was built at end of livil war.
            by Isaac senken he returned from the war circa 1866 </p>
        <p> Later owned by Guy and Mary (Baland?) Lindsay. wat until about 1948. </p>
        <p> Then seened by Henry Strickland until alert 1955 </p>
        <p> Then owned by Elizabeth Ely and later her they graudaughter Lorrie Springer until about
            1985. </p>
        <p> Dana Watrous Cabin </p>
        <p> Originally a fur trappers cabin built by Wade Barmes around Turn of century. </p>
        <p> Later owned by Dana <esc>&amp;</esc> Bertha Watrous 1912 used as thei honeymoon cabin. </p>
        <p> Purchased by Gerald of Langene Ely in 1964 </p>
    </page>
    <page n="5">
        <p> Frank <esc>&amp;</esc> Daisy Ely </p>
        <p> Built their summer cottage ein 1926- </p>
        <p> framework and sheathed from barn across late between old oak tree and Apple nook. </p>
        <p> Theu son Wallace worked in scout comf lach summer fium about 1929 three 1934, as "Handy
            mou" while going to Pen State. </p>
        <p> Alar had son Jerald had some job in camf from 1936 thra 1941. </p>
        <p> You Per owned by Kenneth <esc>&amp;</esc> Yasuke Ely. </p>
        <p> Lather S. Ely Jr. </p>
        <p> Built his summer honed in 1932. See conflate history in detail on separate paper. Nous
            owned by JEEtfit </p>
        <p> Luther S. Ely Sv. </p>
        <p> Built a semner cottage in 1911- located betwen present Kenneth Ely with house <esc>&amp;</esc>
            Juald Ely house. Was moved pieel by bice sast of Kenneth Elyo </p>
        <p> wat by Hama by Herman <esc>&amp;</esc> Edna Ely atts. I. Now owevel by Herme <esc>&amp;</esc> Blodives Otto.
        </p>
    </page>
    <page n="6">
        <p> Dr. Watter C. and Emily Oly Adams </p>
        <p> Cottage built by them in 1935. Presently owsel by Paul <esc>&amp;</esc> atta mae adams Hersart. </p>
        <p> Martha Otto sirton </p>
        <p> Cottage butt about 1998 by Martha senter. 1978 </p>
    </page>
    <page n="7">
        <p> ELT LAKE </p>
        <p> 2 Bocnks for the dinner <esc>&amp;</esc> fellowshib. also thanks for deskrig me to talk tonight </p>
        <p> 86 - Drinking cos ter </p>
        <p> Last Glacier-Kettle Lake </p>
        <p> Studies by universities </p>
        <p> Ammi Ely - lands around Ely Lake </p>
        <p> Home Orana <esc>&amp;</esc> Tom Hakesby </p>
        <p> Canding Mill ab outlet </p>
        <p> on Meteraben Creck Grist mill further devem Lake dammed 10 for power </p>
        <p> Two Farms not owned by A. Ely - Rogers <esc>&amp;</esc> Keat </p>
        <p> Sold to two Rothers Hamelin <esc>&amp;</esc> Shirley Stephens - March - a shad collapsed killing
            all their </p>
        <p> cattk Sharris sale </p>
        <p> Purchased by LS <esc>&amp;</esc> ECEG 1922 </p>
        <p> Same yr Mrs Ritten heurt </p>
        <p> T 10wled trees </p>
        <p> Scouts pouchural in acres (Schoon Hall) </p>
        <p> 19-7 </p>
        <p> Scand's burchiased rest of (8) deres </p>
        <p> 1950 Scante puchamad E.C. Ely foreberly </p>
        <p> Other sites at Ely Luke </p>
        <p> Isaas Bakach- 18205 </p>
        <p> Wada Barnes-1905 </p>
        <p> LSE </p>
        <p> 1911 </p>
        <p> FTE 1926 </p>
    </page>
    <page n="8">
        <p> -LSE Jr. 1932 </p>
        <p> Dm <esc>&amp;</esc> Emily Adams - 1935? </p>
        <p> Martha Garten Feach outs (Romolk) about 1940 </p>
    </page>
    <page n="9">
        <p> Cary starter at 1971 </p>
        <p> MARCH 4, 1922 Edgar a, Ely and Futter of Ely fought the Nent and Ragon form at Ely take </p>
        <p> Ap. 7. 1922 Edgar C. Ely and Lutter <esc>&amp;</esc> Sly sold 41/2 acres of the Rogues fom to
            scradon Girl Scouts, Juar 1927 Ser Edgare Ely and fictter <esc>&amp;</esc> Ely told the degry +
            kone fare to the Ecrantis bil Scouts fon and the Depdds format. 28 1923 Edgar e. Ely
            purchand 10 im at Ely take (90 acryl </p>
        <p> mon 30-1959 the EnC. Ito the Scranton Carl Scouts by <esc>&amp;</esc>c. Elyt Ely form was sold to
            Children, Fahy H. Ety and Marian <esc>&amp;</esc> miller. </p>
    </page>
    <page n="10">
        <col n="1"> labe contid Faunfun Bar Miss Yost-Wallen wether there abad 1929 throw 1935 Huber
            <esc>&amp;</esc> Aste Yeomans wy for LTE <esc>&amp;</esc> Is Fem Franklin <esc>&amp;</esc> Marshall - 250M youll Oild Goh
            fra 16'11" wond it Hay Bam -172C - by FRE </col>
        <col n="2">
            <p> </p>
            <p> From Tabe (1988?) </p>
            <p> Rou </p>
            <p> Fanms Rogers - Kent Kon </p>
            <p> LSENEC you / 90 keres </p>
            <p> 1927 Parohanal remainder of Fore </p>
            <p> And. Ed - Bought Soted to seba atento ants 1948 </p>
            <p> Origined fert </p>
            <p> Isue Balance built aller Ciud </p>
            <p> 10,000 The plated near H. Rad </p>
            <p> 1920? Ma Riffenhouse Brophe grouf ol Kouts </p>
            <p> Parmad to waters eilge </p>
            <p> Shirley <esc>&amp;</esc> lamen Steun </p>
            <p> Sdaria Carm -Bar Show collapsed </p>
            <p> LSE<esc>&amp;</esc>Mp;ECE Goathl al Shene sk </p>
            <p> Prev Charlier Kamb of Bill Cameran </p>
            <p> Fodam </p>
            <p> Kanday mall by Ami - 10' hugker</p>
        </col>
    </page>
    <page n="11">
        <p> MARCH 4, 1922 EDCAR CELY LAND LUTHERS.ELY BOUGHT THE KEHT ANS ROGERS FARMAT ELYLAKE AT A
            SCHERRIES ABLE. THE FORMER GUNGRY WERE HAMILICH ANY SHIRLEY STEVENS. </p>
        <p> APRIL 7. 1922 EN CAR C. AND LUTHER JEG SOLD 42 ACRES OF THE ROGERS FARM TO THE SCRANTON
            GIRL scouts JUNE 19 27 LUTHERS, ELY AND EDGAR C-ELY SOUD THE ROMANING ACRES OF THE KGHT
            AND ROCONG PARK TO THE SCRANTONE GIRL SCOURS. </p>
        <p> JAN, 28 1929 ERCAR CERY BURCHASER THE REYNOLDS PARK ON THE WEST SIDE ORELY LAKE. ABOUT
            NINETY ACRES (90) MAR. 30 1959 THE EDUARCELY PARM WAS SOLD TO THE SERANEOX GIRLSCUNTS,
            BY HIS CHILR REY PAHY ELY AND MARIOVE EMILLER </p>
    </page>
    
    <menu>Settlers Gallery</menu>
    <div class="gallery" imgbase="Images/"  id="earlysettlersgallery">
        <image src="PXL_20250830_151059646"/>  
        <image src="PXL_20250830_151012416"/>  
        <image src="PXL_20250830_151029600"/>  
        <image src="PXL_20250830_151045022"/>  
        <image src="PXL_20250830_151000634"/>  
        <image src="PXL_20250830_150953392"/>  
        <image src="PXL_20250830_150935451"/>  
        <image src="PXL_20250830_150939465"/>  
        <image src="PXL_20250830_150928612"/>  
        <image src="PXL_20250830_150949759"/>  
        <image src="PXL_20250830_151004053"/> 
    </div>
</settlers>
