<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#xBC;">
 <!ENTITY frac13 "&#x2153;">
 <!ENTITY eacute "&#x00E9;">
 <!ENTITY frac12 "&#xBD;">
 <!ENTITY frac23 "&#8532;">
  <!ENTITY frac34 "&#x00BE;">
  <!ENTITY ldouble "&#x201C;">
  <!ENTITY rdouble "&#x201D;"> 
]>
<history xmlns:bibtex="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:wtm="http://wtm.cornell.edu"
    xmlns="http://wtm.cornell.edu" menu="Cottage History" xml:id="cottagehistory">
    <metadata class="main">
        <mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" version="3.3">
            <titleInfo xml:id="cottagehistorytitle" class="maintitle">
                <nonSort>The </nonSort>
                <title>Building of the Luther S. Ely, Jr. Cottage, Ely Lake</title>
            </titleInfo>
            <abstract displayLabel="Content description">
                <wtm:p> The design of the Luther S. Ely, Jr. cottage at Ely Lake was largely
                    inspired by resourcefulness and practicality during the lean times of the
                    Depression era, utilizing available and salvaged materials. Key inspirations and
                    elements included: </wtm:p>
                <wtm:itemize>
                    <wtm:item> Necessity and available materials: The builder, Luther S. Ely, Jr.,
                        used stone from an old wall for the foundation, hemlock trees from Uncle Ed
                        Ely's property for lumber, and lumber salvaged from his father's old poultry
                        house for framing and windows. </wtm:item>
                    <wtm:item> Salvaged materials: Casement windows discarded during a remodeling
                        job at Crystal Lake were used for the front and east living room windows.
                        Lumber from a dismantled ice house provided materials for the front porch. </wtm:item>
                    <wtm:item> Functional needs: The cottage was designed to include a kitchen sink,
                        which was a novelty for cottages on the lake at the time. The front yard was
                        filled with stone to address muddy conditions. </wtm:item>
                    <wtm:item> Personal touches and rustic aesthetic: The builder crafted unique
                        ceiling fixtures for the living room using Juneberry wood, rhododendron, and
                        coconut shells to maintain a rustic look. He also created the &ldouble;owl
                        clock&rdouble; for the living room from old clock works, plywood, and
                        Juneberry wood. </wtm:item>
                    <wtm:item> Adaptation for future needs: The cottage was later modified to
                        include a cellar and an addition for a kitchen, dining area, and bathroom,
                        anticipating its potential use as a permanent residence. </wtm:item>
                </wtm:itemize>
            </abstract>
        </mods>
    </metadata>

    <page n="1">
        <p class="first"><span class="first">Due to the Depression</span> of 1929, the early 1930's
            saw many very lean times. Many banks were closed by government order, many businesses
            were failing and many electrical contractor, in Carbondale who also was City
            Electrician. By 1932 his people were out of work or on &#x201C;part time&#x201D;. I was
            working for Frank Vanilorn, an electrical contractor, in Carbondale who was also City
            Electrician. By 1932 his work was slack and I started my electrical contracting
            business. I rented a one-car garage on Church St. in Carbondale and at first, most of my
            work was small remodelling jobs. </p>
        <p>I tried to borrow fifty dollars at the Pioneer Dime Bank to purchase electrical supplies
            and was told that I had to have property with a building, or buildings, on it for
            collateral. My cottage lot alone was not acceptable. Any spare time that I had I used to
            build a stone foundation on my lot with stone from an old stone wall near my lot. I
            bought a wheelbarrow to move the stones. One July day in 1932, Uncle Ed Ely came over
            from his summer cottage to ask what I was building. I told him that I intended to build
            a cottage sometime when I could afford it. A few days later he asked me to go for a hike
            in his woods, to the top of his steep side hill on the southwest corner. There were
            several large hemlock trees that had been hit by lightning. No one would buy so few
            trees as lumber was plentiful and cheap. He said that I could have the trees if I could
            get them out without damaging the young trees among them. I knew I would have to have
            some help with this job. </p>
        <p>My neighbor, Guy Lindsley, had a porch that was badly in need of repair so I asked him if
            he could use some lumber. He said &#x201C;yes&#x201D; but he could not afford to buy
            any. I told him about the trees and since he had a team of horses and was an experienced
            man with logs, that I would help cut the trees and pay the sawyer's bill if he would
            skid the logs out, take them to the saw mill &#x201C;only one mile away&#x201D; and
            bring the lumber back. He promptly agreed. I asked when he wanted to start and he said,
            &#x201C;as soon as you have lunch.&#x201D; So, about one o'clock we started to fell the
            trees. There were seven nice tall ones and up to 22 inches in diameter. We cut the logs
            in lengths to fit our needs. It was a hot July day and the mosquitoes were out in large
            numbers! Guy brought the lumber back and we shared it fifty-fifty. I stacked my lumber
            near the foundation. The saw mill was a makeshift affair and the lumber showed it. A 2x6
            might be 1 1/2" on one end and 2 1/4" on the other. </p>
        <p>In Carbondale there were two brothers, Niles and Clayton Race, who were excellent
            contractor's carpenters. I did the electrical work on many of their jobs. We
            occasionally went fishing on Crystal Lake, four miles west of Carbondale, where they had
            a boat. It was much like Ely Lake only larger and deeper. I invited them to Fly Lake a
            few times. They were good sports and we had several pleasant fishing trips together. </p>
        <p>One day in January I went to their lumber yard for some material and they were not very
            busy. Work was very slack, especially in the winter. Clayton said they needed some
            exercise and if I would provide dinner for them they would out and put up the framework
            of the cottage. They had seen the foundation and lumber pile during their fishing trips
            there. My sister, Helen, was a good cook and offered to prepare the dinner. We used
            Frank's cottage for the dinner. </p>
    </page>
    <page n="2">
        <p>I bought the groceries, including steak! It was January 15, 1933, a clear cold day. The
            work was started at 8:30 A.M. and with their very efficient system, by 4 P.M. they had
            the frame work all finished and stayed, ready to enclose. Clayton did all of the cutting
            and I helped Miles set the floor joists and the rest of the frame work. </p>
        <p>Any spare time I had I worked on the cottage starting to enclose it. My Father had a good
            poultry house that he no longer used and said that I could have it if I would clean all
            of it up. It contained a lot of good usable lumber and two double sash windows. I was
            able to salvage most of the lap siding and a lot of good nails. The poultry house was 12
            x 24' and not very old. I used my trailer to haul the material to the cottage. </p>
        <p>That same summer the Race brothers were doing an extensive remodelling job, including a
            large addition, to a summer home at Crystal Lake owned by Frank Hemmelwrig Hemmelwright,
            a wealthy family from Scranton. During the remodelling, several very nice casement
            windows were removed and discarded. I asked Mrs. Hemmel-wright if she would sell me
            three of the windows. She asked what I wanted them for and I told her for the building
            of my cottage. She said to take them and I was welcome. I used them for the two front
            and one east living room windows. I used the double sash windows from Dad's poultry
            house, by making them single sash, for the bedroom windows. I made the frames for them
            during the evenings in my father's cellar in Brooklyn. By late fall, I had the cottage
            enclosed and the roof on. There was just enough lumber left to build a 10x10 shed-roof
            type kitchen on the back. I got some used brick and built the chimney and bought a used
            kitchen stove for three dollars. </p>
        <p>The next item was a good used kitchen sink and drain pipe and drain bed for it. This was
            the first cottage on the Lake to have a kitchen sink. Many household items were
            available at very low cost. I bought a good used oak dresser for three dollars and four
            chairs for fifty cents each....a door for the kitchen for one dollar complete with
            hinges and door lock. </p>
        <p>The front yard was very low and muddy. As I came to the cottage one Saturday soon after
            noon, I saw Joseph Jagger with their team of horses and stone boat picking up field
            stone from the meadow across the road from my lot. When I asked Joe where he was taking
            the stone he said to a ravine at one side of the meadow. I told him that I would help
            him if he would haul them to my front yard at the cottage. Joe said, &#x201C;You can
            start right now&#x201D; and we hauled a lot of stone to fill in the yard. They sunk down
            on the soft mud and dried the yard a lot. </p>
        <p>Since my Father no longer used his ice house he wanted it removed. He told me I could
            have it if I would remove it completely. I salvaged a lot of good hemlock boards and 2x6
            chestnut timbers. I tore it all down and hauled the materials to my cottage with my
            trailer. This furnished most of the materials for the front porch. </p>
        <p>We used kerosene Lamps and candles until I wired the cottage for electricity in about
            1935. To keep a rustic look I made two ceiling fixtures for the living room. I used
            Juneberry wood and rhododendron for the candle holder and half a coconut shell for the
            canopy. I built the sockets inside of the candlesticks. All electrical fixtures must
            have an underwriter's seal of approval on them. </p>
    </page>
    <page n="3">
        <p>I placed a sticker in the canopy that read &#x201C;approved by The Ely
            Laboratory&#x201D;. Charles Pierce was the Fire Underwriter's inspector at that time and
            had inspected many of my electrical jobs. The certificate came through with no comments. </p>
        <p> I was relocating electric meters from the inside of buildings to an enclosed meter box
            on the outside for the Scranton Electric Co., doing fifty meters per month for many
            months. I had to dispose of any discarded material, in-cluding lots of various sizes of
            conduit (steel pipe enamelled on the inside). One day a farmer, Harland Meade, came to
            my electrical store which was located at 25 Salem Ave., Carbondale, to purchase an
            electric fence. He had a used shallow well pump for a trade-in on the fence. He had
            tried to use it to do a job for which it was not intended. I allowed him five dollars
            for the pump. </p>
        <p> I put a used electric motor from a junked washing machine on the pump, repaired an old
            pressure switch, found a discarded hot water tank and installed all of these under the
            front porch as there was no cellar under the cottage at that time. I used salvaged
            conduit for water pipe from the Lake to the pump and from the water tank to the kitchen
            sink. Now we no longer had to go to the Lake with water pails. During these depression
            days the practice was USE IT UP MAKE IT LAST WEAR IT OUT. It was surprising what could
            be done if you were serious about it and you could accomplish your objectives as well. </p>
        <p> On several occasions Uncle Ed Ely invited me to his basement shop to spend a winter
            evening with him. Having been a jeweler and watchmaker for many years, he had a supply
            of old clock works. He repaired one of the old eight-day clock works. Then, from a piece
            of plywood, we cut out a large owl and a sakaller one to place beside it. I mounted
            these owls on a piece of curved Juneberry Limb and used eyes purchased from a
            taxidermist in Prompton, Pa. These, combined with the 8-day clock works became the
            living room &ldouble;owl clock&rdouble; which was still running and occupied a place on
            the wall when the cottage became the property of the next Ely generation. </p>
        <p> I think it was in 1934 that I had the first overnight guest. The Harry Jagger family
            lived on the original Ely farm by the Lake, later owned by Maurice Otto. When I arrived
            at the cottage on a late Saturday afternoon, Joe Jagger called to me asking if I had a
            large frying pan. When I told him that I did, he said that he would be down in a short
            time. The Jaggers had recently butchered a beef and Joe came with at least two pounds of
            freshly ground beef, and began filling the large frying pan with it. I told him that we
            could not possibly eat all of that but he assured me that it would be no problem. We had
            a fine dinner of potatoes and gravy, another vegetable and bread and of course, the beef
            patties. Since Joe's parents had gone away for the week-end, I suggested that he stay
            all night there with me to which he agreed. He asked if I had an alarm clock and
            although I did not he decided that he would probably wake up by 5 A.M. anyway to milk
            the cows. When we went to bed we had forgotten that Jagger's dog, Tige, had come with
            Joe. The next thing I remember was waking in the morning to hear Joe talking. Tige had
            come up to our bedroom, gone to the side of the bed where Joe was sleeping and had
            licked Joe's face to waken him. Tige was an extremely good cow dog and knew it was time
            to go get the cows. </p>
    </page>
    <page n="4">
        <p>I had to keep my store open until 9 P.M. on Saturdays so it was usually near 10 when I
            got to the lake. Tige was usually there at my back door wagging his tail and waiting for
            me. When he heard my truck coming down the road he would run down across the meadow to
            greet me. One Sunday morning, Harry Jagger said to me, &#x201C;You got home a little
            late last night.&#x201D; I asked him how he knew that and he said, &#x201C;That's easy!
            Tige sleeps in a rocking chair on the porch and when he jumps out of the chair, the back
            of the chair hits the side of the house with a bang!&#x201D; Tige was an unusual dog and
            a friend of all the lake people. We had a special pair of glasses which had no lens and
            a corn cob pipe for Tige. We took some interesting pictures of him wearing the glasses
            and with the corn cob pipe in his mouth. I am sure Joe could tell many interesting
            experiences relating to Tige but that is another story. </p>
        <p>Edith Lowry and I were married on February 22, 1936. That summer we lived at the cottage
            and in the fall rented a small house in Carbondale. Each summer we spent at the lake and
            had a nice garden back of the cottage. We both enjoyed fishing and caught many nice
            walleyed pike and a few nice trout. A little at a time during this period, I finished
            the second floor. </p>
        <p>I think it was in 1935 that I made a twelve foot row boat using white pine lumber. I made
            it in the living room of the cottage. </p>
        <p>The first electric refrigerator we had was one that I took as a trade-in on a new
            Frigidaire. It was heavy but worked well and I believe that to this day it is in the
            Herman Otto cottage. </p>
        <p>In the winter of 1941 Edith had surgery at Sayre Hospital. We stayed with her Mother in
            Uniondale when she came home at the request of both she and her Mother, until she was
            feeling better. War had started in Europe and it was quite evident that this country
            would be involved. Edith suggested that we should prepare the cottage for a possible
            residence due to the uncertain future so... </p>
        <p>I took the kitchen off, jacked the cottage up and hired help to excavate a cellar. I
            hired a &#x201C;Mr. Ross&#x201D; from Dalton and his helper, &#x201C;Pedro&#x201D; to
            lay the foundation wall. I hauled scrap quarry stone in my trailer, using any spare time
            I had both mornings and evenings. The quarry was located in the Scout property East
            woods and was operated by William Burbank and Harry Robinson from Brooklyn. We made the
            foundation large enough for an addition on the back and as soon as it was finished I
            built the addition for the kitchen, dining area, clothes closet and a bathroom. </p>
        <p>I built the kitchen base cabinets and installed a new sink. I also put a new water pump
            in the basement and a suction pipe four feet deep to the lake. The suction end was at a
            depth of twenty feet. I hired Gene Sykes from Harford to build the chimney. He had
            nearly enough buff colored bricks left from another job to build ours. He had to finish
            it with just a few red bricks near the top. </p>
    </page>
    <page n="5">
        <p>He said it was so that when I came home I would be able to tell which cottage was mine.
            The total cost of the chimney, which incidentally is flue-lined, was $35.00. </p>
        <p>About this same time, the Race Bros. in Carbondale purchased a larger building for their
            lumber business and needed a new and larger electrical main entrance and distribution
            panel. I did the work but did not charge them for labor. This was done in appreciation
            for their putting up the framework for my cottage. I mention this as a typical example
            of the many cases where labor was exchanged thoughout the entire area during this time
            period. </p>
        <p>Early in 1942 I worked finishing the inside of the cottage. Edith was there part of the
            time, helping me wherever she could and enjoying the progress we were making. Late in
            June, while at her Mother's in Uniondale, the cancer for which she had undergone surgery
            earlier, rapidly progressed. She died on August 6, 1942. </p>
        <p>In mid-August I received a notice from the Draft Broad. About this same time I also
            received a letter from Kenneth Cornwell offering me a job as an instructor in a Naval
            electrical school in Harrisburg for the duration of the war. I turned it down and
            enlisted in the Navy in Philadelphia as a rated electrician. This was mid-September. I
            felt it was the duty of any single man. I had no desire for the Army. I had had enough
            unpleasant experiences with pup-tents. </p>
        <p>My time at the lake was rapidly running out so I had to hire two carpenters to build the
            upper cupboards in the kitchen, build the arch separating the kitchen and dining room,
            and make doors for the living room and bathroom. </p>
        <p>I returned from the Navy in mid-September 1945. My first project was to complete the
            bathroom. I hired Sam Ring to excavate for the septic tank and the drains. One cold day
            I had to go to Montrose and told Sam that I had left the doors un-locked so that he
            would have a warm place to eat his lunch. When I returned around 4 P.M. he was gone. My
            nephew, Frank C. Ely was returning home from school and told me that Sam Ring was lying
            in the road part way up the hill. Frank agreed to help me get Sam back home which was
            about 2 miles. We got him to his parent's front porch and as I rapped on the door, Sam's
            pants fell down around his shoes. His Father quickly got him inside the house. In the
            cellar I had about a quart of methigelum <footnote>A mead wine made from honey, water,
                and spices.</footnote> my Father had made several years earlier. There was also half
            a gallon of wine. Sam had a great thirst for such liquids.. ......... That Fall I had
            all of the bathroom fixtures installed. During the winter months by doing a little bit
            each day, I put rock wool insulation bats in all of the outside walls and panelled the
            living room. I had sustained a back injury during my tour of Naval duty and could only
            work a few hours most days. </p>
        <p> On four different occasions I saw deer swimming in the lake. One nice buck swam from the
            outlet to the Scout Camp. A buck and a doe swam from Otto's side directly across the
            lake. </p>
    </page>
    <page n="6">
        <p>I had installed a large pail-a-day hot water heater in the basement and connected it to a
            large hot water radiator in the living room. By keeping a coal fire in that and one in
            the combination coal and electric range in the kitchen, I had no problem keeping warm in
            spite of the temperature being 30 degrees below zero for three nights in a row. </p>
        <p>During the War I travelled over 180,000 miles on the water and over 8,000 miles by
            railroad. I had crossed the Atlantic fourteen times. When I came home it seemed that
            everyone wanted to me GO SOMEWHERE. All I wanted for awhile was to stay in one place!
            That is the reason I named the cottage DUNROMIN, with the hope that people would take
            the hint! </p>
        <p> After the Ely family home in Brooklyn was sold the lake became home port for many family
            members. Never knowing who might arrive over the week-end, the doors of the cottage
            remained unlocked on Friday and Saturday nights. Herman and Edna Otto often came from
            Harrisburg. On one Saturday morning I awoke about 6 A.M. and found my brother-in-law,
            Dr. Walter Adams, in bed with me. Other family members were in another bedroom. I
            started to quietly get out of bed when Walter said, &#x201C;Where are you going?&#x201D;
            I said that I was going to get breakfast. He said he was going with me and &#x201C;let's
            have pancakes and sunfish.&#x201D; It did not take us long to catch the sunfish and
            prepare breakfast. The family had arrived late, during the night and come in without my
            hearing them. </p>
        <p> In 1947 I replaced the bedroom windows with double sash windows. The old windows were
            used the following summer in the tree farm cabin where they are still in use. I also
            replaced the east living room window with a double window. </p>
        <p> Sometime in the 1960s I had new shingles put on the roof. In the late summer and fall of
            1972 I put a new floor on the porch and installed new posts and porch railings. The
            concrete step for the front porch was poured the day Tom Jagger was born. </p>
        <p> I am not certain but believe it was early in the 1950s that I built the outdoor
            fireplace. I inquired at Hallstead Iron Foundry to see if they made grill tops. One of
            the owners, Mr. Hall, said that they did not and asked what they looked like, so I drew
            a brief sketch for him. He told me to make a grill of plywood, exactly the way I wanted
            it, to sand it smooth, and they would make one of cast iron. When I told brother, Frank,
            about it, he said that he too would like to have one. So I made my plywood pattern and
            took it to the Foundry. When I went back in about two weeks as Mr. Hall had suggested,
            he took me on a tour of the foundry first and then proceeded to personally sand blast
            the top of the grill smooth. It cost twelve cents per pound for the castings. I used a
            large, flat scrap quarry stone for the base and built the fireplace on it. I could bake
            pancakes as fast as a dozen people could eat them on my new grill. The grill was ideal
            for many things including cooking fish. The last known wall-eyed pike caught in the lake
            in the summer of 1964 by Dale Girton and myself was cooked on it along with several
            other large fish. </p>
    </page>
    <page n="7">
        <p> </p>
        <p>Mary Lindsey lived in the house now known as the &#x201C;farm house&#x201D;. She had a
            woodshed she wanted to sell. The south side of it was missing, there was no floor and it
            actually was just a shell. I paid her what she asked for it -- fifteen dollars. Now I
            had to move it. Joe Jagger engineered the job and helped me put two long elm skids under
            it, one on each side, with a cross beam on each end. Nearby, a man was doing some
            grading with a small bulldozer. He pulled the woodshed up the old roadway, a distance of
            about 150 ft., and I moved it sideways to its present location. First, two new sills
            were put under it; then floor joists and a floor and finally the door and windows. I
            needed a storage area for garden tools, wheelbarrow, etc. so I made this building into
            my shop. Uncle Everett Ely told me this had originally been the woodhouse for the
            Chestnut Hill School House located near the top of the hill. He recognized it by the
            framework where the corner frames were held together by large wooden pegs. These are
            still very visible on the west side of the building. </p>
        <p>The original family cottage was built in 1911 and the three Ely brothers took turns
            staying there with their families. My Father and Uncle Everett each had a horse and
            buggy as did most other people in the area. That was the only means of local
            transportation. Uncle Ed had a Chalmers automobile. The three brothers soon built a shed
            which had two stalls one for the horse and the other for the buggy or one stall could be
            used by Uncle Ed to get his touring car in out of the weather. The original metal roof
            is still on this building. (We have since called it the garage.) When my brother, Frank
            made his permanent residence at the lake, he installed the sliding doors and padlocks,
            both of which are now on the garage. Frank also built the shed attached to the west side
            under which he could house his trailer. </p>
        <p>Jeanne and I spent several summers at the lake. Every year there was more and more
            maintenance to be done. We tired of painting the cottage so had it vinyl sided. The two
            original storm doors needed repair and we replaced them with aluminum storm doors. With
            our residence in New Milford, the 65-acre tree farm and the cottage all requiring our
            time and energies, we realized that every to enjoy the summer we were spending more time
            maintaining the properties and less time left the lake. The time had come to make some
            decisions. We spent the winter months contemplating what to do. By spring we knew we
            needed to reduce our responsibilities by one and decided to pass the lake property on to
            another generation to enjoy. Our prime desire was to keep it in the Ely family. The
            majority of immediate Ely family members either already owned lake property or lived in
            such distant locations as to make ownership at the lake prohibitive. Jerald's family,
            being local, seemed the most likely prospects. We discussed all of this with both Jerald
            and LeJune. After much consideration and several more discussions together, they decided
            they would like to purchase it themselves which they did in the spring of 1986. </p>
        <p> That same summer, Jerald and Junie invited us to the cottage for a family picnic. As we
            enjoyed the picnic and the many conversations we observed younger family members playing
            in the yard, some were fishing from the dock, others out in the Lake swimming. Everyone
            seemed so happy and was enjoying the day. We left with pleasant memories and the
            satisfaction of knowing we had made the right decision. </p>
        <p> February 7, 1989 </p> <image src="LutherSignature"/> <p> Luther S. Ely, Jr. </p>
    </page>
</history>
