<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#xBC;">
 <!--ENTITY frac13 "&#x2153;"-->
  <!ENTITY frac13 "1/3">
 <!ENTITY eacute "&#x00E9;">
 <!ENTITY frac12 "&#xBD;">
 <!--ENTITY frac23 "&#8532;"-->
  <!ENTITY frac23 "2/3">
  <!ENTITY frac34 "&#x00BE;">
  <!ENTITY ldquo "&#x201C;">
   <!ENTITY rdquo "&#x201D;">
]>
<botantical xmlns:bibtex="http://bibtexml.sf.net/" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:wtm="http://wtm.cornell.edu"
    xmlns="http://wtm.cornell.edu" xml:id="botanticalstudy">

    <metadata class="main">
        <mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" version="3.3">
            <titleInfo xml:id="botanicaltitle" class="maintitle">
                <title>Botanical Survey of Ely Lake</title>
            </titleInfo>

            <abstract displayLabel="Content description">
                <wtm:p> This section details a botanical and ecological survey conducted at Ely
                    Lake over four days in August, 2019 by Timothy A. Block, University of Pennsylvania. ​ </wtm:p>
                <wtm:itemize>
                    <wtm:item> The lake is characterized as a natural glacial kettle-hole lake with
                        a pH range of 8.5 to 8.8, indicating alkalinity. ​ </wtm:item>
                    <wtm:item> Limited plant diversity is noted, with a predominance of emergent and
                        floating-leaf species, and no nonnative aquatic plants observed. 
                    </wtm:item>
                    <wtm:item>The survey
                        lists various native and introduced plant species, emphasizing the
                        ecological importance of the lake despite its low species diversity.
                    </wtm:item>
                </wtm:itemize>
            </abstract>
        </mods>
    </metadata>

    <page n="1">
        <p class="title" xml:id="botanical">Botanical Survey of Ely Lake, Susquehanna County, PA in 2019, July 9-10 and August 15-16. </p>
        <p>Timothy A. Block, Ph.D., the John J. Willaman Chair of Botany, Morris Arboretum of the
            University of Pennsylvania. </p>
        <p class="first"><span class="first">It was my privilege</span> to be invited to Ely Lake by
            Anne Wain for the purpose of conducting a botanical and ecological survey. Anne
            graciously coordinated obtaining permissions from all of the lake's landowners for
            access and specimen collecting activities. My sincere thanks to Anne and all the Ely
            family folks with whom I shared a wonderful meal and much great conversation. Also, many
            thanks to Eileen Head who coordinated access to Camp Archbald and arranged for my use of
            one of their boats. </p>
        <p>Ely Lake is quite remarkable for its physical and ecological parameters, yet possessed of
            somewhat limited plant diversity. This, as noted below, is perfectly normal, indeed
            quite favorable, for a lake with Ely's characteristics. </p>
        <p>In spite of the lowering of the water level in the 1890s to regulate water flow to a
            carding mill downstream on the outlet, Ely Lake retains much of the character of a
            natural glacial kettle-hole lake. The consistency of steep slopes into the water
            suggests that Ely Lake has existed in close to its current configuration since its
            formation approximately 16,000 to 17,000 years ago at the end of the Wisconsinan
            Glaciation. Most glacial kettle-holes are characterized by significant sediment
            infilling over time, resulting in an ecological transition to bog, and ultimately return
            to forest. This natural successional process appears almost completely arrested at Ely
            Lake. </p>
        <p>Although far from a conclusive analysis, a handheld pH meter registered readings of 8.5
            to 8.8 at several spots at the surface of the lake. These readings place Ely Lake near
            the alkaline end of the pH range (typically 4.5 to 9.0) for lakes in northeast
            Pennsylvania. Most natural glacial lakes register pH readings of 6.0 or lower, often
            much lower, meaning that they are acidic. The higher pH of Ely Lake, and others like it,
            is generally due to influx of water (springs) that has moved through calcite-rich strata
            in the Catskill Formation (or, perhaps, Huntley Mountain Formation) that underlies this
            region of Pennsylvania. Large pieces of rock, testing positive for calcite content, were
            found in the streambed of the outlet stream in August 2019. The full geological
            explanation for this phenomenon is well beyond the scope of these notes. The botanical
            upshot of the alkalinity of Ely Lake is that high pH limits the number and types of
            aquatic plant species that can live there. </p>
        <p>As noted above, most of the shoreline is steep-sided leaving relatively little shallow
            substrate for inhabitance by plant species that require water depths of about three
            feet, or less. Another physical limitation to the lake area available for plant
            colonization is the prevalence of overhanging tree canopy around much of the lake
            margin. Aquatic plants often germinate in the shade, but rarely survive to adulthood. </p>
        <p>The lake is nearly continuously ringed by a narrow band of emergent species dominated by
                <plant profile="POCO14">pickerelweed</plant> (Pontederia cordata), <plant
                profile="SPAM">bur-reed</plant> (Sparganium americanum), and <plant profile="DUAR3"
                >threeway sedge</plant> (<plantsci profile="DUAR3">Dulichium orundiaceum</plantsci>)
            nearer the shore, and another relatively narrow band of floating-leaf plants variously
            dominated by <plant profile="NYOD">white waterlily</plant> (Nymphaea odorata), <plant
                profile="BRSC">watershield</plant> (Brasenia schreberi), and <plant profile="NULUV"
                >spatterdock</plant> (Nuphar variegata) beyond. This superficially appears to
            represent the classic aquatic vegetation zonation pattern, with the exception of the
            fact that there is almost no zone of submergent plant species beyond the floating-leaf
            species due to the rapid drop-off of the substrate to depths of 10 feet or more. At
            least four species of <plant profile="POBI9">pondweeds</plant> (Potamogeton spp.) were
            collected in relatively shallow water in openings of the canopy of the floating-leaf
            species above. Most significant of these is <plant profile="PORO2">Robbin's
                pondweed</plant> (Potamogeton robbinsi) which is listed as Pennsylvania Rare (PR) by
            the Pennsylvania Natural Diversity Inventory. Three other Potamogeton species collected
            remain to be identified. No non-native aquatic plant species were observed.</p>
    </page>
    <page n="2">
        <p> In spite of the fact that Ely Lake has somewhat limited plant species diversity, this in
            no way diminishes the biological or ecological importance of this very special body of
            water. People sometimes mistakenly equate low species diversity with &ldquo;less
            important&rdquo; ecosystems. Nothing could be further from true! Proper evaluation of
            ecosystems rests on functionality, not species diversity. It appears to me that the
            aquatic system at Ely Lake exists (and has for a long time) in a relatively steady
            state. </p>
        <p> It is of utmost importance to continue to limit outside access to the lake, especially
            the use of outside watercraft which are often vectors for the introduction of non-native
            species of plants and other organisms. I also strongly recommend limiting any
            disturbance near the shoreline. Seeds and other plant propagules often reach the water
            by surface flow across unvegetated areas. </p>
        <p> Although not comprehensive, the following table lists the species observed in the July
            and August, 2019 visits to Ely Lake and its immediate environs. </p>
        <menu>Botanical Report</menu>
        <table id="botanical" latex="llll" menu="Botanical Report" xml:id="botanical">
            <caption>Plant species observed at Ely Lake, July and August, 2019</caption>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <th>Species</th>
                    <th>Common name</th>
                    <th>Growth habit</th>
                    <th>Nativity</th>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <tr profile="ACRU" photo="003_shp">
                    <td>Acer rubrum</td>
                    <td>red maple</td>
                    <td>tree</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="ALSU" photo="002_shp">
                    <td>Alisma subcordatum</td>
                    <td>water-plantain</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="AMAR3" photo="001_shp">
                    <td>Amelanchier arborea</td>
                    <td>shadbush</td>
                    <td>tree</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="BEAL2">
                    <td>Betula allegheniensis</td>
                    <td>yellow birch</td>
                    <td>tree</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="BELE">
                    <td>Betula lenta</td>
                    <td>sweet birch</td>
                    <td>tree</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="BOCY">
                    <td>Boehemeria cylindrica</td>
                    <td>false nettle</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="BRSC">
                    <td>Brasenia schreberi</td>
                    <td>watersheild</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="CAGY4">
                    <td>Carex gynandra</td>
                    <td>sedge</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="CACA18">
                    <td>Carpinus caroliniana</td>
                    <td>hop hornbeam</td>
                    <td>tree</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="CIMA2">
                    <td>Cicuta maculata</td>
                    <td>water hemlock</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="CIAR2">
                    <td>Cinna arundinacea</td>
                    <td>wood reedgrass</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="COAM2">
                    <td>Cornus ammomum</td>
                    <td>silky dogwood</td>
                    <td>shrub</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="CORA6">
                    <td>Cornus racemosa</td>
                    <td>gray dogwood</td>
                    <td>shrub</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="DUAR3">
                    <td>Dulichium arundinaceum</td>
                    <td>three-way sedge</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="ELAC">
                    <td>Eleocharis acicularis</td>
                    <td>needle spike-rush</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="ELPA3">
                    <td>Eleocharis palustris</td>
                    <td>creeping spike-rush</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="FAGR">
                    <td>Fagus grandifolia</td>
                    <td>American beech</td>
                    <td>tree</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="HAVI4">
                    <td>Hamamelis virginiana</td>
                    <td>witchhazel</td>
                    <td>tree</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="IMCA">
                    <td>Impatiens capensis</td>
                    <td>touch-me-not</td>
                    <td>herbaceous annual</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="IRVIS">
                    <td>Iris versicolor</td>
                    <td>blue iris</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="ISOET">
                    <td>Isoetes sp.</td>
                    <td>quillwort</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="JUEF">
                    <td>Juncus effusus</td>
                    <td>soft rush</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="KALA">
                    <td>Kalmia latifolia</td>
                    <td>mountain laurel</td>
                    <td>shrub</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="LEOR">
                    <td>Leersia oryziodes</td>
                    <td>rice cutgrass</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="LIBE3">
                    <td>Lindera benzoin</td>
                    <td>spicebush</td>
                    <td>shrub</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="LOCA2">
                    <td>Lobelia cardinalis</td>
                    <td>cardinal flower</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennia</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="LUPA">
                    <td>Ludwigia palustris</td>
                    <td>water-purslane</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="LYAM">
                    <td>Lycopus sp.</td>
                    <td>water horehound</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="LYNU">
                    <td>Lysimachia nummularia</td>
                    <td>moneywort</td>
                    <td>herbaceous annual</td>
                    <td>Introduced</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="LYTE2">
                    <td>Lysimachia terrestris</td>
                    <td>swamp candles</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="MIRE">
                    <td>Mitchella repens</td>
                    <td>partridge berry</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="NAGR">
                    <td>Najas gracillima</td>
                    <td>slender water niad</td>
                    <td>herbaceous annual</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="NULUV">
                    <td>Nuphar variegata</td>
                    <td>spatterdock</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="NYODO">
                    <td>Nymphaea odorata</td>
                    <td>fragrant water-lily</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="ONSE">
                    <td>Onoclea sensibilis</td>
                    <td>sensitive fern</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="OSCL2">
                    <td>Osmunda claytoniana</td>
                    <td>interrupted fern</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="OSCI">
                    <td>Osmunda cinnamomea</td>
                    <td>cinnamon fern</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="PIST">
                    <td>Pinus strobus</td>
                    <td>white pine</td>
                    <td>tree</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="POBI9">
                    <td>Potamogeton bicupulatus</td>
                    <td>pondweed</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="POEP2">
                    <td>Potamogeton epihydrus</td>
                    <td>ribbonleaf pondweed</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="POPU7">
                    <td>Potamogeton pusillus</td>
                    <td>pondweed</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="PORO2">
                    <td>Potamogeton robbinsii</td>
                    <td>Robbins' pondweed</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="POCO14">
                    <td>Pontederia cordata</td>
                    <td>pickerelweed</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="PRSES">
                    <td>Prunus serotina</td>
                    <td>wild black cherry</td>
                    <td>tree</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="SALA2">
                    <td>Sagittario latifolia</td>
                    <td>arrowhead</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="SCTA2">
                    <td>Schoenoplectus tabernaemonta</td>
                    <td>giant bulrush</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="SCGE2">
                    <td>Scirpus geargianus</td>
                    <td>bulrush</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="SODU">
                    <td>Solanum dulcamara</td>
                    <td>climbing bittersweet</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Introduced</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="SPAM">
                    <td>Sparganium americanum</td>
                    <td>bur-reed</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="THPA">
                    <td>Thelypteris palustris</td>
                    <td>marsh fern</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="TRVI2" photo="hyvi4_1h">
                    <td>Triadenum virginicum</td>
                    <td>swamp St. John's wort</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="TSCA"
                    photo="https://plants.sc.egov.usda.gov/ImageLibrary/standard/tsca_002_shp.jpg">
                    <td>Tsuga canadensis</td>
                    <td>eastern hemlock</td>
                    <td>tree</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="TYLA">
                    <td>Typha latifolia</td>
                    <td>cattail</td>
                    <td>herbaceous perennial</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
                <tr profile="VACO">
                    <td>Vaccinium corymbosum</td>
                    <td>highbush blueberry</td>
                    <td>shrub</td>
                    <td>Native</td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </table>
    </page>
</botantical>
